<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two manifesto's, or declarations; the one by the King of Denmarke, the other by the Queene of Sweden, both concerning the present warres.</title>
            <author>Denmark. Sovereign (1588-1648 : Christian IV)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79538</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3936</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E45_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23311</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871962</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871962</idno>
            <idno type="VID">154484</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79538)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 154484)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 8:E45[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two manifesto's, or declarations; the one by the King of Denmarke, the other by the Queene of Sweden, both concerning the present warres.</title>
                  <author>Denmark. Sovereign (1588-1648 : Christian IV)</author>
                  <author>Sweden. Sovereign (1632-1654 : Kristina)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 3d 1644".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian, --  King of Denmark and Norway, 1577-1648.</term>
               <term>Kristina, --  Queen of Sweden, 1626-1689.</term>
               <term>Dano-Swedish War, 1643-1645 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sweden --  History --  1523-1654.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="manifesto_or_declaration">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:154484:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TWO <hi>MANIFESTO'S,</hi> OR DECLARATIONS; THE ONE By the King of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> THE OTHER By the Queene of <hi>Sweden,</hi> both concerning the preſent Warres.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>HRISTIAN the Fourth, by the Grace of God, of <hi>Denmarke, Norway</hi> of the <hi>Gothes</hi> and <hi>Vandals,</hi> King; Duke of <hi>Holſtein, Shleſwigk, Stormarn</hi> and <hi>Ditmars,</hi> Count of <hi>Oldenburg</hi> and <hi>Delmenhorſt &amp;c.</hi> To his <hi>Roman</hi> Imperiall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, all Chriſtian Kings and Princes; as alſo to all and every one, of what quality, degree and dignitie ſoever hee bee Greeting: Making withall knowne, how and in what manner Wee (by an unexpected hoſtile invaſion of the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Army, under the command and conduct of Fieldmarſhall <hi>Leonhard Toſtenſohn,</hi> firſt into our Principalities of <hi>Shleſwigk, Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtein</hi> and Dominions belonging thereunto, and thereupon into our Province of <hi>Iutland</hi> immediately belonging to our Crowne of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke</hi>) inevitably are compelled to put to the view of all and every one by this <hi>Manifeſtoe,</hi> the Injuſtneſſe of this wrong and action, and to the better manifeſtation hereof, to draw in briefe hither thoſe Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that have beene made betwixt our Kingdome and the Crowne
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:154484:2"/>of <hi>Sweden,</hi> whereby not onely all Controverſies are fully laid up, a perpetuall peace concluded, but alſo, how in future time, if any nigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourly errours ſhould come to paſſe it ſhould be carried, was provided and agreed upon. Whereas now in the yeare 1560. when <hi>Ericus</hi> King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> the 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of that Name, ſought all manner of pretences a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our Father King <hi>Frederick</hi> the Second of happy memory, and thereby gave occaſion to a long during bloody Warre, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the ſame by the mediation of the Emperour <hi>Maximilian,</hi> of the Kings of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Poland,</hi> as alſo of the Elector of <hi>Saxony</hi> in the yeare 1570. being compoſed, by their mediation the aforeſaid perpetuall Peace was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, which both Kings, and their Succeſſours and Heires, together with their Kingdomes, by their Royall Honour Faith and troth ſhould be bound to keep upon paine and forfeiture of a million of gold. It was alſo agreed upon namely that, if ſo any errours ſhould come to paſſe, the deciſion thereof by the appointed Counſellers of State of both ſides, and if ſo be they could not agree upon a finall certaine concluſion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that one ſide had as many voyces as the other, it ſhould be put to an Arbitratour; But if ſo be that one of the Kings would not ſtand to all what was concluded, in ſuch a caſe the Counſell of State and the Subjects ſhould be diſcharged of their Oath and dutie, and ſhould not be bound to follow and obey the King ſo long till he hath conſented to it, as appeareth at lage by the Copie Lit. <hi>A.</hi> And the ſame agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment have beene confirmed againe anew betwixt Us and the deceaſed King <hi>Guſtavus Adolphus</hi> Lit.<hi>B.</hi> of happy memorie in the yeare 1612. and in the yeare 1624. ſome errours, which then would ariſe, by the appointed Counſellers of State were compounded and laid by. Wee have alſo thereupon kept and maintained good and neighbourly cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence with the aforeſaid King <hi>Guſtavus Adolphus</hi> all the dayes of his life, and afterwards with the moderne Queene and State, and We had no other opinion of the Crowne of <hi>Sweden,</hi> but that it would doe the like. And it appeareth moſt clearly by that, that for thoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares together we have endeavoured with much zeale and care to take off from the ſame the heavie burden of warre in the <hi>Roman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and to ſettle the ſame in Peace and tranquility; Whereas, if any bad <hi>talentum</hi> or miſtruſt had beene in our heart againſt that Crowne, We had juſtly ſuffered the ſame to ly under ſuch burden, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:154484:2"/>according to common practiſe <hi>Per vicinorum diſcordias &amp; bella,</hi> ſought peace and ſecurity of our Kingdome and Dominions. But being no contrary intention againſt the ſame, as alſo no ill ſuſpition of the ſame ſticked with us; So therefore no ſuch Counſells could find place with Us, but rather ſtrived, to procure for the ſame a true and firme Peace as Wee can teſtifie with God and a pure conſcience, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we ſought with an upright heart and minde no prejudice to the ſame, but the good and welfare of both contending and fighting par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. To which end alſo in the yeare 1629. preſently after the agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment betwixt the <hi>Roman</hi> Imperiall Majeſty and Us, Wee deſired His Imperiall Majeſties conſent of an amiable Treatie betwixt Him and the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> and how we have received thereupon a deſired anſwer; and the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> alſo thereupon accepted our interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, and appointed a Dyet at <hi>Dantzigk</hi> in the beginning of the year 1630. where the <hi>Roman</hi> Imperiall Majeſtie had his Ambaſſadour, a Burgrave of <hi>Donaw</hi> but no Treatie was taken in hand, becauſe no body appeared there in the name of the Crown of <hi>Sweden:</hi> However wee did therefore not ſuffer our good intention to ſinke, but cauſed preſently after the King of <hi>Swedens</hi> death the reaſſumption of ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable work further to be ſollicited, and deſired of the Counſell of State, or rather of the Rixchancellour <hi>Oxenſtern,</hi> who was at that time <hi>Plenipotentiaerius</hi> in <hi>Germanie,</hi> who alſo according to his letter <hi>(Lit.C.)</hi> to our Counſell of State, bearing date <hi>Collen</hi> on the <hi>Spree</hi> the fourth of <hi>Febr.</hi> 1633. accepted it with much thankes, and that therefore the Crowne and Princeſſe was much obliged to us for it, but eſpecially at that time was faine to confeſſe, that Our peaceable minde about for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer commendable actions was more then enough known unto Him; And repeated that ſame alſo afterwards upon another occaſion (as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth out of the Extract <hi>(Lit.D.)</hi> to Us his Letters bearing Date at <hi>Franckeford</hi> the 17. of <hi>May,</hi> in the ſame yeare. Afterwards alſo Wee have ſent Our Ambaſſadour at great charges to <hi>Breſlaw,</hi> which Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſage hath likewiſe been in vain and fruitleſſe: Then We urged ſtil further the propounded Treatie for a happy Peace, till at laſt after ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny teadious, long during and many times fruitleſſe employed paines and endeavour, Wee by Gods gracious permiſſion brought it ſo farre, that the Potentates and Princes, that have intereſt in this ſo long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:154484:3"/>bloody war in <hi>Germany,</hi> after a long and teadious Treatie ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly agreed in <hi>Praeliminaribus,</hi> and therupon with the conſent of all ſides, a meeting for the treaty of a generall Peace was appointed to bee at <hi>Oſnabrugge.</hi> When the Imperiall and <hi>Swediſh</hi> Ambaſſadours had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready met there with Our Ambſſadours, the King of <hi>France</hi> alſo had given notice of the comming of His Ambaſſadours, And the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> alſo were neere at hand, ſo that every one ſtood in good hope, that now at laſt the long deſired Treatie would goe on, and produce ſome proſperitie and happineſſe by the reduction of a generall Peace, and Wee in a ſpeciall manner directed onely Our thoughts and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell that way<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> how by Gods gracious aſſiſtance this worke ſo well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun we might further and thereby deſerve thankes of whole Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, as <hi>Oxenſtern</hi> himſelfe in the above ſaid Extracts declares: Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding Wee were faine to ſee and heare with our griefe and ſorrow, that upon a ſudden the <hi>Swedes</hi> had all things overthrowne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. For when Wee, by reaſon of the alledged Agreement and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacie, could expect no ill from them and to Our knowledge alſo have not offended them, or if ſo be they had to pretend any of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, they ſhould have turned it over to the aforeſaid, and oftentimes repeated, confirmed, and practiſed Deciſions and agreements; yea, when they ſhewed all love and amitie towards Us, and had our ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Reſident with them, and theirs againe with Vs, and then further their Ambaſſadour appointed for the treatie of Peace, conferred al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt daily with Our Ambaſſadours as appointed Mediatours, and pretended every where nothing elſe but neighbourly love, peace and concord. Then they cauſe by their Generalls (in a hoſtile manner) Our Countries and Dominions about 60 leagues at length from the utmoſt Frontiers of our Principalities to be invaded and taken, till they may come into our Kingdome<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which they then eaſily could performe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Wee feared no Hoſtility, but under the pretence of amitie, with any foregoing (being uſuall with all honeſt Nations) denouncing of warre upon a ſudden ſurpriſed the Countries, that the Subjects ſaw them in the midſt of them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> before they could heare any thing of their comming, ſo that for 30. leagues together they found no man in armes excepting 50. men in a Fort neere the Eaſt Sea, which by night time they skaled, and tooke it, impriſoned the Governour and detaine him
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:154484:3"/>ſtill. Yet in the meane time our Rix-Marſhall in our abſence guarded our Frontiers with ſome horſe, and for their defence began to raiſe a Sconce, and withall ſent a Letter to the above-ſaid <hi>Swediſh</hi> Generall to learne and know the reaſons and motives of ſuch an invaſion, &amp; what further We had to expect from him, as the Copie <hi>Sub Lit. E.</hi> ſhewes more largely. But the aforeſaid Generall kept the Trumpeter that was ſent with him, and left the Letter unanſwered, till he fell againe upon a ſudden without any forewarning with his whole ſtrength of horſe and foot, and Artillerie upon Our horſe, and drove them, (their number being much leſſe then his) into the aforeſaid Sconce, where he preſently begun to batter with his Cannon, the aforeſaid Sconce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not yet finiſhed, and continued it for 4. dayes together. But when the reſt of his Infantry and the great Cannons that he expected came to him, he anſwered the aforementioned Letter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wherein hee imputed the reaſons of his taking quarters in <hi>Holſtein</hi> and other neighbou ing Countries, to neceſſitie, but that he purſued the gathered troopes, and without ſummoned the aforeſaid Sconce; Hee pretended to be for his owne ſecuritie, as <hi>ſub Lit.</hi> F. is to be ſeene. And being they lay onely in garriſon there ſome of the Trained Bands, and the ſame alſo as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, was brought to no perfection, hee tooke it preſently, forced the ſouldiers to lay downe their armes, inſomuch that whole <hi>Iutland</hi> he ruinated, and waſted the Principalities with intollearable Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution and Plundering, and to paſſe by other enormites, Our Officers of the State and Gentry hee cauſed to be detained priſoners and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves farre worſe then Chriſtian enemies: And it is eaſie, what of the aforeſaid moſt prejudiciall and proud Letter may be jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and concluded; and moreover that by this ſo hoſtile invaſion and proceedings he aimed not meerely at ſome Provinces, nor at a meere recruting of the Armie, which however he ought not to ſeeke in our Countries without Our conſent, but rather that it is intended meere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of a hoſtile proud and haughtie purpoſe and hope, to deſtroy Vs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> our Kingdomes, Countries and People.</p>
            <p>The true and proper cauſe of this ſo hoſtile reſolution againſt us, is as yet unknowne unto us, but wee can eaſely gueſſe, that the hate againſt us and the envy to the floriſhing peaceable condition of our Kingdomes and Countries together with the moderne occaſion of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:154484:4"/>their having in their hands a brave <hi>German</hi> Army, and our ſecurity wee have put in thire friendſhip, hath principally moved them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto: And we are aſſured<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that not any other cauſe, that according to all Divine and humane right is ſufficient to ſuch an unforwarned hoſtility, can iuſtly be produced. And though there were ſome, that might have given them occaſion to this ſpilling of blood, yet <hi>modus procedendi</hi> can never bee iuſtified neither before God nor men. For the moſt high God hath no delight in the iuſteſt and moſt neceſſary warre. How ſhould hee then approve of ſuch unneceſſary warres, whereunto no cauſe was given. And as he hath ſworne by his truth, that he will bring the Covenant, upon which he hath given his hand, and afterwards broken it, upon his owne head: So without all doubt will revenge in due time this uniuſtneſſe and wrong, that hath beene done to confederats and fellow members of the ſame ſaith under the pretence of Friendſhip, contrary to e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ected contracts, covenants and agreement; Neither will it bee approved by any man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that ever hath loved honeſty and vertue; becauſe according to the Lawes and cuſtomes of all Nations, to a lawfull warre not onely weighty rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but alſo that the ſame, before they come to extremities, be made kowne to the Adverſary party are required. Which is counted alſo ſo much ſeeming to the naturall right and common equity, that the adverſary party hath allwayes beene held diſhoneſt and injuſt; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when by publicke contracts it is provided, that otherwiſe ought not bee done. It may bee there will be pretended, that on the Swediſh ſide, that what hath paſſed with thire ſhips in the ſound, is alledged to bee a lawfull cauſe of this warre againſt us. But wee doe not doubt, when all impartiall men doe firſt know, how to the arreſting of the Swediſh Ships by reaſon of ſo manifold kowne and diſcovered deceitfullneſſes, wee have beene compelled, and how farre wee have procceded with particular merchants not <hi>de facto,</hi> but meere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>ſecundum juſtitiae norman,</hi> that if there hath beene made complaint of the firſt ſentence that was given in the firſt inſtance, wee our ſelfe (to teſtifie the more our deſire to impartiall iuſtice, together with our Counſell of ſtate) have reaſſumed the hearing of the cauſe, that then no man for uſing our right will condemne us; eſpecially when by us in ſuch a hearing, more was ſeene upon the preſervation of neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:154484:4"/>friendſhip, then what the law required. Where now for the ſtaying and arreſting of three, or at moſt foure ſhips, ſo bloody a warre may preſently begin amongſt Chriſtians, wee let the whole world judge. And principally by the riſing of any grievances there; ſhould have beene followed the way that is preſcribed in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts and agreements; then, if the matter had not beene remedied, the way to extremities had yet ſtill beene open: to which end our Counſell of State have ſufficiently declared themſelves, and offered nothing elſe, but a firme peaceable intention, and that in the like dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences that ſhould happen, the aforementioned ancient contracts and agreements ſhould be followed: albeit the aforeſaid Swediſh Government hath no weighty cauſe to complaine: For no man al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in <hi>Europe</hi> is to be found that hath burned ſo much the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce with <hi>Tolls</hi> and cuſtomes and yet without right and equity, which our Subjects by thire cuſtomes, which heretofore they have laid at <hi>Dantzgik,</hi> in the <hi>Pillaw,</hi> and as yet take upon the eaſt ſea at <hi>Roſtock</hi> and in whole <hi>Pomerania</hi> have heavily felt, And though they had not the leaſt right to it, yet ſo ſharpe was therewith proceeded, that neither our owne proper goods, nor our Sonnes, though thire paſſes have beene produced, have beene free of it. Which though it cannot be excuſed with any right, hath become a farre greater and heavier grievance, which hath dured theſe many yeares; however for all that, we intended not to diſturbe further the Common-Weale not to occaſion the ſpilling of more Chriſtian blood; But in caſe the <hi>Swedes</hi> ſhould thinke, that by the proceeding in the ſound againſt ſome few of thire Ships, though not without right and equity, they had yet ſufficient cauſe to this warre, ſurely every one would the more perceive our uprightneſſe towards them, conſidering that though in that way a farre greater, and a farre more inexcuſable cauſe to warre by the aforenamed proceedings hath beene given to us, and that the like opportunity, as they apprehended now, nor the brave pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers of thoſe, that highly laboured to draw us alſo into the play, wee have not wanted: notwithſtanding wee would neither this, not that, ſuffer to move us, for to undertake any thing againſt Conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience Religion, Contracts and agreements: whether alſo all that, what was lawfull to the <hi>Swedes</hi> contrary to the word of God and the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:154484:5"/>naturall equity, be not alſo permited to us, we would faine know, wherein hath ſinned the raigning Duke of <hi>Holstein</hi> and the other Dukes of the <hi>Sonderburgiſh</hi> line, which alſo neither the nigh conſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinity with the Queene nor <hi>Communia Sacra</hi> could ſave. All this we muſt commit to God, who is an enemy to all bloodthirſty and falſe hearts, but wee doubt not at all but that the whole impartiall world will now eaſily judge, and cleerly conclude out of theſe inexcuſable proceedings againſt us of the Swediſh intention and deſigne of the moderne warre how falſely the defence and preſervation of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion as a finall cauſe of thire taking up of armes, hath hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terto beene pretended; when they make no conſcience to fall out with us as a Proteſtant Potentate without any neceeſſity, right and cauſe, and to ruinate wholly our poore Subjects, that in whole <hi>Europe</hi> no Proteſtant King, Electour or Prince may bee free of mine. Whether now in ſuch a way the Proteſtant Religion be defended, or whether there be holpen to the ruine thereof, I feare that all Proteſtants will feele to late with thire owne ruine and griefe, yea that this warre is begune only for the ruine and perdition of the Proteſtants, whereas hereby the neighbouring Proteſtant Cities, Commons and Subjects are highly prejudiced in trade and traffique, the already ruinated neighbours, which hitherto have provided themſelves againe out of our Country with all neceſſaries which had thire onely refuge thither, will not little grieve. To paſſe by<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> what hurt and dammage this warre by the totall deſolation of <hi>Germany</hi> will bring to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Churches and Schooles; In ſo much that Gods Holy name al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo muſt be to the <hi>Swedes</hi> a cover for their falſehood and ill inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. But being our innocency appeareth ſufficiently out of that, which hath beene ſaid above, and the Swediſh <hi>Modus procedendi</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us ſtands thus, that every one of the neighbours may take an example thereof and provide in time for his ſecurity, much leſſe, theſe that afe in alliance with the ſaid Crowne, aide or aſſiſt them as tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is ſaid <hi>Adinjuſta bella nulla eſt obligatio.</hi> For confedracies admit al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes this exception, when a lawfull cauſe is forced upon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and firſt no faire accord findes place then not afore they take their effect, which both on the Swediſh ſide is put aſide, and they rather meerely <hi>audendo &amp; bella ex bellis ſerendo</hi> thinke to grow great: And therefore thire
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:154484:5"/>confederates ought to take the more heed, and not permit them, nor truſt them too much, leſt forgetting all faithfulneſſe and reſpect to Confederates, they may not ſhew them the ſame unfaithfull and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neighbourly part, that they have ſhewed to Us and divers others, eſpecially being by ſuch deſtructions of Treaties of Peace not Wee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, but alſo all Potentates and Princes, that helpe to further them ſeriouſly, yea in generall all Chriſtian hearts, that have abhorred the cruell ſpilling of blood, and miſerable ruines of Countries, which for ſo many yeares together have ſo miſerably overwhelmed a great part of Europe, and on the other ſide ſought heartily and earneſtly the re-eſtabliſhing of a happy generall Peace, have beene offended and hindered in their commendable purpoſe. For now it is as cleare as day-light, with what earneſtneſſe &amp; mind, the Crown of <hi>Sweden</hi> hath hitherto deſired a peace in <hi>Germany,</hi> whereas not onely themſelves have diſturbed the enſuing Treatie, but beſides began alſo a new war, without any juſt cauſe meerely as haters of peace, as alſo, that the Commerce and Trafficque, that hitherto in ſome manner hath yet beene uſed in the Eaſt and Weſt Sea<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by theſe troubles and diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, is ſtopped and brought to confuſion is onely to bee imputed and aſcribed to them as unruly and ſhameleſſe authours thereof. Wee hope therefore, that every one will ſeriouſly take to heart this unchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian and heathen-like attempt, and bee jealous of the blo d thirſtie; and on the other ſide afford to Us, (that have not onely beene hindered againſt Our will in the wholſome purpoſe to turne off further ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Chriſtian blood as alſo deſtruction and deſolation of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, but alſo without any forewarning have beene in a hoſtile man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſubdued, ſurpriſed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and beene robbed of Our owne,) a helpfull hand, and their beſt aſſiſtance to recover the ſame againe. And eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially Wee truſt firmely, that the juſt and omnipotent God, who ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horres all Actions breaking Covenants and Peace, will fatherly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect Us, and yet powerfully maintaine Us in that, what graciouſly He hath beſtowed upon Us.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given at our Citie of <hi>Ottenſea</hi>
                  <date>the 30. of <hi>Ian.</hi> 1644.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="manifesto_or_declaration">
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:154484:6"/>
            <head>The Queene of <hi>Swedens</hi> Declaration or manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoe concerning the invaſion into the Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of the King of <hi>Denmarke.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>HRISTINA by the grace of God conſtituted Queene and hereditary Princeſſe of the <hi>Swedes, Gothes</hi> and <hi>Vandalls,</hi> Great Princeſſe of <hi>Finland,</hi> Ducheſſe of <hi>Ehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten</hi> and <hi>Careliae,</hi> Counteſſe of <hi>Ingarmanlend</hi> &amp;c. To all our truſty and well beloved Nobility Gentry and Clergy, to all and every one in particular of our truſty and well beloved Subjects and inhabitants in our Kingdome of <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> Principalities of <hi>Finland, Liefland</hi> and <hi>Ingermanland</hi> Greeting. Theſe are to give you and all and every one of you graciouſly to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that for thoſe many years paſt we have ſeen, and could plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perceive, how &amp; in what manner our, Neighbour the King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marck</hi> in theſe heavy times contrary to our friendly truſt and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence we put in him, hath ſought all occaſions and opportunities to hinder not onely our expedition in <hi>Germany</hi> againſt our and the Kingdomes profeſſed enemies, and to ſtop the way for the attainng unto a good, true and firme peace (albeit he hath tryed and offered ſometimes both in words and writing to perſwade us the contrary,) but alſo eſpecially hath ſtrived to throw into our way many other roubles, in practiſing our and our Native Countries worſt, as much as poſſibly he could doe. For firſt during this German warre he hath troubled both ſecretly and openly our Armies and out landiſh affaires and alwayes made our burden to us more heavy and troubleſome, and ſometimes often with good words, ſometimes alſo by force ſought to put us out of all our advantages, neither hath omitted alſo to deſpiſe and defame us and our Kingdome as much as poſſibly he could. Afterwards in theſe latter times he hath openly ſtop't many of our Subjects, eſpepcially thoſe, that uſed to have ſhipping and trade through the Sound, and by unlawfull ſtaying and arreſting of of the Swediſh ſhpis hindered thire living and trade, and beſides al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo againſt all equity impoſed and charged our Subjects, in <hi>Liefland</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:154484:6"/>and <hi>Narva,</hi> that trade in the Weſt ſea, with double, yea triple cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome; But alſo upon ſome, eſpecially upon the tranſportation of ſuch Swediſh commodites, which he ſaw and perceived, would encreaſe the Trade and Merchandize, and make our Subjects to proſper as namely ordnances, Lead, Armes, and the like; he hath laid a prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition to take away thereby the workemanſhip here in our Native Country, and to keepe us and you under his ſubiection, Wherefore we truly perceiving a ſecret warre had iuſt cauſe, according to our duty, wherewith in our high and Royall office to our loyall Subjects for their defence and protection wee are bound to take upon us this unſufferable oppreſſion, and thire grivance; But conſidering the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous times and ſeaſons of this age, wee rather bore the like injury and wrong, then that wee ſhould enter into any quarrell, or take up armes againſt the King of <hi>Denmarck,</hi> perſwading our ſelves, of two evill and troubleſome occaſions; to be the beſt to ſuffer and beare it with ſilence, to hope a good alteration, and meane while to ſeeke that all miſunderſtandings and grievances may be removed by friendly and peaceable meanes. And therefore ſome few yeares paſt by way of our letters memoriall, which we ſent to Servant and agent now reſident in <hi>Denmarck</hi> have ſought to prevent and remove the afore ſaid grievances, but in ſtead thereof for thoſe three yeares together, we had returned unto us from him, nothing elſe but ſcornefull words, and a denying anſwer. Now in this laſt yeare paſt he went therewith ſo farre and made it ſo groſſe, that directly contrary to all neighbourly friendſhip, and confidence, uſuall cuſtome, and cleare accords and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſions of the Kingdomes, as alſo contrary to all Lawes, Rights, and naturall courſe and property of Trade, without giving any war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to us and our Subiects, the Swediſh ſhips and goods, which arrived in the ſound, and had their uſuall Certificats, as hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was aggreed upon, not only two or three, but as many there have beene of one and the ſame value and were laden with coſtly wares, which (after that they were forced to pay cuſtome and Accyſe of the Sweediſh Goods contrary to the ſaid deciſions and agreements of the Kingdomes. By the deaniſh ſerchers have beene ſearch't with a number of indiſcreete ſouldiers guarded, &amp; carryed up to <hi>Coppenhagen,</hi> where afterwards the letters and writings have beene opened, torne
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:154484:7"/>in peeces, and partly taken away; Cheſts and packs, broken and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and the goods taken out and unladen; and when all that was done, the King of <hi>Denmarke</hi> made himſelfe not onely Judge over the Deciſions and agreements of the Kingdomes, but alſo appointed and put his other Servants to judge over it which heretofore was neither uſuall, nor in any way agreeable with the aforeſaid inland agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Deciſions much leſſe ought Wee in our Royall Highneſſe and Kingdomes Right to, ſuffer and endure it, without the utter ruine and deſtruction of you and all Our loyall Subjects.</p>
            <p>And after that Our Subjects in ſuch a manner have been detained and burdened with unuſuall courſes of law, the cuſtome firſt of all was taken of them, and afterwards both Ship and Goods from them, and thoſe, whom their own was adjudged and declared free, have beene arreſted again anew, &amp; guarded wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h the watch, yea at laſt alſo both their ſhips and goods were taken by force from them. And albeit Wee (having ſeene him more and more to proceed with all manner of enmitie and hatred, together with new plots in his unjuſt purpoſe and deſigne, miſuſing the dangerous times of this age and eſpecially the heavie warres, where with Wee and our Native Countrie have beene burdened, and that all this is nothing elſe but an open wrong and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurie) tooke to heart our loyall Subjects wrong and their complaints, which they have made to Us about it, and this laſt Summer paſt cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed our loving <hi>Rix</hi>-Counſellours to diſpatch ſeverall Letters, as is u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall to the <hi>Rix</hi>-Counſellours of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> and therein cleerely ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them and intimated unto him the unjuſtneſſe of the matter, and that the like unjuſtneſſe and wrong is contrary to the League, Deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and agreements of the Kingdomes, hoping and deſiring that they would ponder and conſider rightly our reaſons, and the nature of the cauſe it ſelfe, prevaile ſo farre with their Maſter the King, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure that to our innocent Subjects which have ſuffered and endured ſuch like conſiderable hinderances, and intollerable loſſes, their Ships and goods might be reſtored without any dammage, Merchandizing and trading be reduced to its former courſe; as alſo the Deciſions of the Kingdomes according to former cuſtome, and as it ought to bee, may be inviolably kept, and maintained. But they returned Us not onely a number of vaine excuſes and groundleſſe remonſtrances, but
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:154484:7"/>beſides alſo contrary to all friendly neighbourly confidence, as alſo ſuch preſſing friendly viſitation with Letters<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Wee were faine to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, and to underſtand really and indeed, that the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> was not onely not in the leaſt way altered and changed in his ſet thoughts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and evill deſigne, to deſtroy and ruinate Us and our Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects but rather was hardned in his purpoſe, and augmented the grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances and burdens more and more, dealt with Vs and our Subjects in a more deſpightfull and hoſtile way<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as before, and thus actually diſſolved all neighbourly friendſhip league and agreements, which in antient times have been made betwixt the Kingdomes, which mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while ought to be obſerved, and Hee not leſſ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then Wee to maintaine the ſame inviolably, ſeeking thereby to make unto Us ſhipping and trading betwixt the Eaſt and Weſt Sea ſo heavie and intricate, that the ſame muſt fall of it ſelfe, to ſeparate Us thereby from Commerce, and Communication with the other Nations in the world, which God and Nature by way of ſhipping hath granted to Us, and to our deare native Countrie and Kingdome: But principally to deprive Vs and Crown the of our meanes, and our Subjects of their living and encreaſe, and to force Us and You to pay Tribute and Cuſtome to him, and that not according to equitie, but as much as himſelfe pleaſeth, as it hath happened in theſe later yeares, ſeeking thereby to bring Us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch a ſtate and condition, that Wee may not enjoy the good, wherewith God hath bleſſed Us in our Kingdome, or make uſe of it for our<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and our native Countries defence and encreaſe. And if this ſhould be longer ſuffered, not only ſhipping and trading (without which our Kingdome cannot ſubſiſt) will be cut off from Us, but alſo all Fiſhing, which Our Subjects uſe for their maintenance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by raiſing of the Salt would be quite ſpoyled and brought to nothinng: As alſo all ſorts of Mines, Smiths forges, and many other trades, which have beene erected with our and the Crownes, as alſo many of Our Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, great and conſiderable charges and coſts, and are now in full uſe and practiſe, would periſh and lay waſt. So many thouſand men, that have undertaken it, and ventured all their eſtates in it, thinking to ſeeke thereby their trade and living, would be brought to their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ruine and deſtruction. Moreover, alſo Wee are certainly infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:154484:8"/>and know it ſufficiently, in what manner hee hath had, and hath yet daily in hand many Plots and Conſpiracies to ſtirre up and entice more enemies againſt Us and our native Countrie. Whereas now by theſe Deſignes and Plots of the King of <hi>Denmarke</hi> that have beene laid by him, and are here rehearſed and alledged, it doth clearely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, what he intended againſt Us and ous deare native Country; So Wee (Hee having actually in ſuch manner, and otherwiſe in many other wayes affronted Us, laid aſide all reſpect to Us, to all Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, League and Deciſions of the Kingdomes, and Wee hereafter having nothing more certaine to expect from him then an open war) have beene highly forced and neceſſitated to let fall the reſpect and peaceable confidence, which hitherto Wee have put in him, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit our juſt cauſe to God, and to proſecute the ſame againſt him, to take up armes for the maintenance of our Royall Highneſſe, for the defence of our native Country, and protection of Our Subjects, and to uſe them with the helpe of the moſt high God, ſo long againſt him and the Kingdome of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> till he doe accommodate himſelfe to equity, and Wee can be ſecured gainſt further wrong, and Wee will not ſtay, that He according to his former cuſtome ſhall draw warre upon ſuddenly and unawares. And therefore to the furtherance of this our Chriſtian and peaceable intention. Wee were faine to cauſe Our and the Kingdomes Counſellour, <hi>Fieldmarſhall,</hi> Our truſtie and welbeloved <hi>Leonhard Torstenſon,</hi> with our Armie in <hi>Germanie</hi> to come into His Country and Principalitie of <hi>Holstein,</hi> and to take his Winter quarter there, and to keepe a watchfull eye to his plots, hoſtile deſignes, and Wee on this ſide with our Domeſtick Armie to put our ſelves into ſuch a Militarie poſture for the defence of the Kingdome, as the danger of the preſent times require, and Wee could doe, leaving all to God and complaining that Wee are forced and neceſſitated to this quarrell, withall wiſhing, that God Almightie would turne off from Us and you all misfortune, looke upon our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie, and moſt graciouſly maintaine and aſſiſt Our juſt cauſe.</p>
            <p>And whereas Wee cannot thinke otherwiſe, but that this will bee ſtrange to many, eſpecially to thoſe that heretofore heard either little or nothing of it, or alſo are informed thereof perverſly by ſome
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:154484:8"/>Adverſaries; Wherefore Wee thought it needfull to diſcloſe unto you Our loyall Subjects in generall, the condition and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the buſineſſe by theſe Our gracious Lettets, and to make it knowne unto you, withall graciouſly deſiring, that yee as lo all Subjects, and lovers of your native Countrie will rightly conſider the aboveſaid and other reaſons, and ponder them well, what hath moved Us hereunto, and Wee enevitably were forced to reſolve to all that, againſt all perverſe perſons, interpret them with a good opinion, and judge thereof rightly and juſtly. And moreover, that you your ſelves will be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to take care for your welfare and ſafetie, that with an una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous concord, and faithfull aſſiſtance, you doe deprive Our enemies and Adverſaries, which plot and practiſe Our and your ruine, of all their courage and haughtineſſe, and cauſe them to let fall their conceited hope, and ſcornfull minde in ſeeking to hate Us farther, and at laſt quite to oppreſſe Us.</p>
            <p>And whereas Wee make no doubt of God goodneſſe, and liberall aſſiſtance; So Wee will hope alſo, that if you (as Wee graciouſly expect from you) doe faithfully ſupport Us in the Expedition of this great Cauſe, with all your ſtrength, valour and Concord, that Wee then with Gods gracious aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance ſhall ſo much the ſooner, and ſpeedier, ſecure and free not onely our native Countrie, but alſo Us and you, all and every one of you from further unjuſt extortion, wrong and injury of Our neighbours, which Wee ſtrive highly for, and ſpare no labour, care, paines and trouble for to attaine there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto; And your faithfulneſſe towards Us upon all occaſions, Wee ſhall reward and recompence you all, and every one of you, with all Royall graces and affections; And thus Wee commit you, all and every one of you, into the gracious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of God Almightie.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:154484:9"/>of <hi>Sweden.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>In witneſſe whereof Wee have confirmed this with Our Royall Signet, and the Subſcription of the reſpective Tutours and Adminiſtratours of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</signed>
               <dateline>Given at <hi>Stockholm</hi>
                  <date>the 16. of <hi>January, Anno</hi> 1644.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>L.S.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Matthias Soop</hi> in the place of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes Sewer.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jacobus de la Gardie</hi> Marſhall of the King<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Sweden.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Carl. Gyldenhelm Rix</hi>-Admirall.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Axel Oxenſtierna</hi> Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Sweden.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Gabriel Oxenſtierna</hi> Baron of <hi>Morby</hi> and <hi>Lindholm,</hi> and Treaſurer of the Kingdome of <hi>Sweden.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
               <date>
                  <hi>May</hi> 3. 1644.</date>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
